# CHRISTINE YIFENG CHEN

Postdoctoral Research Staff Division of Nuclear and Chemical Sciences Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory 7000 East Ave, Livermore, CA, USA Last updated June 24, 2022

cychen@llnl.gov +1 (925) 422-8008

#### Research Bio

I am a geologist and geochemist broadly interested in applications of radiochronometry to terrestrial paleoclimatology and nuclear forensics. At LLNL, I am developing radiochronometry methods for nuclear materials and investigating radiogenic isotopic fractionation processes in the nuclear fuel cycle. I also research applications of uranium-series geochronology to lacustrine carbonates to reconstruct past changes in Earth's hydrological cycle. This work has involved field mapping and characterization of paleoshorelines and porous carbonate build-ups called tufas in the high-altitude central Andes and western United States, two presently water-limited areas where my work will inform our understanding of past climate change impacts on water availability.

#### Positions

- 2021 Postdoctoral Researcher. Chemical and Isotopic Signatures Group, Nuclear and Chemical Sciences Division, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.
- 2020–2021 O.K. Earl Postdoctoral Scholar Research Associate. Geological & Planetary Sciences, California Institute of Technology (Caltech).
- 2013–2019 Research and Teaching Assistant/Fellow. Earth, Atmospheric & Planetary Sciences, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT).

#### EDUCATION

- 2019 Ph.D. in Geology, MIT/WHOI Joint Program.
  - Thesis: U-Th Dating of Lacustrine Carbonates
  - Committee: David McGee (MIT; advisor), Kristin Bergmann (MIT), Andrew Ashton (WHOI), Jay Quade (U. of Arizona), Tim Lowenstein (SUNY Binghamton)
- 2013 A.B. in Geosciences, summa cum laude, Princeton University.

  Thesis: Revisiting the deformed high shoreline of Lake Bonneville
  Advisors: Adam Maloof and Jeroen Tromp

# AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

- 2021 LLNL Excellence in Publication, Physical and Life Sciences Directorate.
- 2019 Caltech O.K. Earl Postdoctoral Fellowship.
- 2019 MIT Larry G. Benedict Leadership Institute Award.

For dedication to empowering fellow students to develop as leaders and being an active mentor to peers within the MIT community.

- 2018 Best Student Oral Presentation Award (1 of 2 awarded total), IPA-IAL Meeting.
- 2017 MIT Martin Family Society of Fellows for Sustainability.
- 2017 MIT Office of Graduate Education Wellington and Irene Loh Fund Fellowship.
- 2016 MIT Dept. of Earth, Atmospheric, and Planetary Sciences Award for Excellence in Teaching.
- 2013 MIT Office of Graduate Education Ida M. Green Fellowship.
- 2013 NSF Graduate Research Fellowship.
- 2013 Princeton Arthur F. Buddington Award.
- 2012 Princeton Benjamin F. Howell Junior Independent Work Prize.

# RESEARCH GRANTS

- 2016 Geological Society of America (GSA) Charles A. & June R. P. Ross Research Award.
- 2016 GSA Farouk El-Baz Student Research Grant for Desert Research.
- 2016 The Explorers Club Exploration Fund, Mamont Scholars Program.
- 2016 American Philosophical Society, Lewis and Clark Field Research Fund.
- 2015 National Geographic Society Young Explorers Grant.
- 2015 Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution Ocean Ventures Fund.
- 2012 Princeton Stanley J. Seeger Research Fellowship for Hellenic Studies.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- PUBLISHED/ACCEPTED [PEER REVIEWED]
- [11] Rodbell, D.T., Hatfield, R.G., Abbot, M.B., **Chen, C.Y.**, et al. (2022) 700,000 Years of Tropical Andean Glaciation. *Nature*. doi: 10.1038/s41586-022-04873-0 Accepted.
- [10] Fendrock, M., Chen, C.Y., Olson, K.J., Lowenstein, T.K., McGee, D. (2022) A computer vision algorithm for interpreting lacustrine carbonate textures at Searles Valley, USA. *Computers and Geosciences*, 105142. doi: 10.1016/j.cageo.2022.105142
- [9] De Cort, G., Chevalier, M., Burrough, S., **Chen, C.Y.**, Harrison, S.P. (2021) An uncertainty-focused database approach to extract spatiotemporal trends from qualitative and discontinuous lake-status histories.

  \*Quaternary Science Reviews, 258:106870. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2021.106870 [EarthArXiv]
- [8] Cooperdock, E.H.C., **Chen, C.Y.**, Guevara, V.E., Metcalf, J.R. (2021) Addressing Systemic Bias In the Lab, Field, and Classroom. *AGU Advances*. 2:1, e2020AV000353. doi: 10.1029/2020AV000353
- [7] Woods, A., Rodbell, D.T., Abbott, M.B., Hatfield, R.G., **Chen, C.Y.**, Lehmann, S.B., McGee, D., Weidhaas, N.C., Tapia, P.M., Valero-Garcés, B.L., Bush, M.B., Stoner, J.S. (2020) Abrupt Arctic Warming Repeatedly Led to Glacial Retreat and Drought in the Eastern Tropical Andes During the Last Glacial Cycle. *Nature Communications*, 11:5135. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-19000-8 [EarthArXiv]
- [6] Chen, C.Y., McGee, D., et al. (2020) U-Th dating of lake sediments: Lessons from the 700 ka sediment record of Lake Junín, Peru. Quaternary Science Reviews, 244:106422. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2020.106422 Invited research article. [EarthArXiv]
- [5] Hatfield, R.G., Stoner, J.S., Solada, K., Morey, A.E., Woods, A., Chen, C.Y., McGee, D., Abbott, M.B., Rodbell, D.T. (2020) Paleomagnetic constraint of the Brunhes age sedimentary record from Lake Junín, Peru. Front. Earth Sci., 8:147. doi: 10.3389/feart.2020.00147
- [4] Austermann, J., Chen, C.Y., Lau, H.C.P., Maloof, A.C., Latychev, K. (2020) Constraints on mantle viscosity and Laurentide ice sheet evolution from pluvial paleolake shorelines in the western United States. Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 532:116006. doi: 10.1016/j.epsl.2019.116006
- [3] Hatfield, R.G, Woods, A., Lehmann, S.B., Weidhaas IV, N., **Chen, C.Y.**, Kück, J., Pierdominici, S., Stoner, J.S., Abbott, M.B., Rodbell, D.T. (2019) Stratigraphic correlation and splice generation for sediments recovered from a large-lake drilling project: an example from Lake Junín, Peru. *Journal of Paleolimnology*, 1–18. doi: 10.1007/s10933-019-00098-w
- [2] Chen, C.Y. and Maloof, A.C. (2017) Revisiting the deformed high shoreline of Lake Bonneville, *Quaternary Science Reviews*, 159, 169–189. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2016.12.019
- [1] Husson, J.M., Maloof, A.C., Schoene, B., **Chen, C.Y.**, Higgins, J.A. (2015) Stratigraphic expression of Earth's deepest  $\delta^{13}$ C excursion in the Wonoka Formation of South Australia, *American Journal of Science*, 315, 1–45. doi: 10.2475/01.2015.01
- Other Publications and Writing (Non-Peer Reviewed)
- Chen, C.Y. (2020) Asian Americans & Pacific Islanders in Geosciences: Introductory Remarks at the 2020 AGU Fall Meeting Meet-Up. [Medium]
- Chen, C.Y. (2020) Diversity and Inclusion in Quaternary Sciences. Quaternary Times, 42(2). November.

#### INVITED SEMINARS

- 2022 Univ. of Wash., Seattle, School of Oceanography. Banse Early Career Scholar Seminar. February.
- 2021 University of Geneva, Department of Earth Sciences. June.
- 2021 Universität Bern, Institute of Geological Science. May.
- 2021 University of Nevada Las Vegas, Department of Geoscience. March.
- 2021 Univ. of Wash., Seattle, Earth & Space Sciences, Distinguished Lecture Series. February.
- 2021 Univ. of Victoria, School of Earth & Ocean Sciences Seminar. February.
- 2020 Vanderbilt Univ., Earth & Environmental Science, EES Seminar Series. November.
- 2020 Lawrence Livermore National Lab, Nuclear & Chemical Sciences Division. October.
- 2020 WHOI, Dept. of Marine Geology & Geophysics, Paleoclimate Seminar. May.
- 2020 Caltech, Division of Geological and Planetary Sciences, Geology Club Seminar. February.
- 2019 Brown Univ., Earth, Environ. & Planetary Sciences, Climate & Environment Lunch Bunch Series.
- 2019 MIT, EAPS, Chemical Oceanography, Geology, Geochemistry, and Geobiology Seminar.
- 2019 USGS, Menlo Park. Informal Brown Bag Seminar.
- 2018 SUNY Binghamton, Dept. of Geological Sciences, Invited Speaker Seminar.
- 2018 Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, Columbia Univ., Biology & Paleo-Environment Seminar.
- 2018 Harvard University, Earth & Planetary Sciences, Solid Earth & Planetary Science Seminar.

#### Conference Talks \*Denotes invited.

- 2019 \*AGU Fall Meeting, invited speaker for Carbonate Sediments Through Time session.
  - "A Tufa Nut to Crack: The Timing and Duration of Lacustrine Tufa Formation in the Late Pleistocene."
- 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, speaker for Advances and Applications in Quaternary Geochronology session.
  - "The 700-kyr Sediment Record of Lake Junín, Peru: Lessons for U-Th Dating Lake Sediments."
- 2019 \*EGU General Assembly, invited speaker for Limnogeology: Reading the Geological Record of Lakes session.
- 2019 Northeast Section Geological Society of America Meeting.
- 2019 Pacific Climate Workshop (PACLIM). Pacific Grove, CA, USA.
- 2018 \*Utah Geological Survey, Utah Dept. of Natural Resources, Lake Bonneville Geological Conference.
- 2018 Goldschmidt. Boston, MA.
- 2018 IPA-IAL Joint Meeting ( $\times 2$ ). Stockholm, Sweden.
- 2015 AGU Fall Meeting. San Francisco, CA, USA.
- 2015 Graduate Climate Conference. Woods Hole, MA, USA.

#### IN THE MEDIA

- Seven Ways PIs Can Counteract Systematic Bias Now. Eos. March 2021. http://bit.ly/20FT1jm
- Teaching Geoscience History in Context. Eos. March 2021. http://bit.ly/3c2NKey
- Geoscientists Explore Scientific Racism in the Teachings of a Princeton Pioneer. *Princeton Alumni Weekly*. January 2021. http://bit.ly/3sAHeBX
- An Ice Sheet's Footprint on Ancient Shorelines. Eos. February 2020. https://bit.ly/3iKhzAm
- Featured scientist in National Geographic Kids Almanac 2020. May 2019. https://bit.ly/3nuT127
- James Hansen's legacy: Scientists reflect on climate change in 1988, 2018, and 2048. Salon, Grist. June 2018. https://goo.gl/3ttnK6
- What Natural 'Bathtub Rings' Teach Us About Climate Change. *National Geographic*, Facebook video. March 2017. Cumulative 1.8 million views. https://goo.gl/cvRDTH
- Scientists Politely Troll Bill Nye The Science Guy, Bill Responds Brilliantly. *IFLScience*. May 2017. https://goo.gl/PyUAGj
- Telltale 'Bathtub Rings' Reveal Ancient Rainfall, Oceanus Magazine, Vol. 52, No. 1, Summer 2016.
- Answers in the Andes: Scientists look to ancient lakes to predict where climate change is heading, Neil Murthy. *Medill Climate Change News*, November 2015. https://goo.gl/oH3fkM

# Undergraduate Advising and Mentorship

- Maya Morris '22 (UC Merced), Summer 2021.
- Valeria Torres-Olivares '22 (Princeton), Pace Center for Civic Engagement RISE (Recognizing Inequities and Standing for Equality) Initiative, Summer 2020.
- Ruth Tweedy '20 (MIT), 2019–2020 Senior Thesis. Tufas from Salar del Huasco, northern Chile.
- Zixuan "Crystal" Rao '18 (USTC, China), Summer 2017, Spring 2018 Senior Thesis. Tufas from Lagunas Miscanti, Miñiques, and Pampa Varela. (Now at Princeton for Ph.D.)
- A.J. Iversen '20 (MIT), Spring 2018–2019 and 2020 Senior Thesis. GIS-based reconstructions of paleolake area and volumes in the western United States and central Andes. Poster presentation at Northeastern Section GSA Meeting, March 2019.
- Jade Fischer '21 (MIT) and A.J. Iversen '20 (MIT), Winter 2018 (participation in fieldwork). Project: Testing heliotropism of columnar tufas in Searles Lake basin, California.
- Jasmine Jin '19 (MIT), Summer 2017.
- Ashling Neary '16 (MIT), Fall 2014.
- Kaylee Brent '17 (MIT), 2015 Grad-Undergrad Mentorship Program.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Contributor and co-organizer of GeoContext, a project dedicated to creating educational materials that provide social and political context for the geosciences. https://geo-context.github.io/
- Teaching Assistant for International Geobiology Course, 3-day petrography unit, 2018 & 2019. Lead instructor: Kristin Bergmann.
- MIT Kaufman Teaching Certificate Program, Summer 2017.
- Guest lecturer for Massachusetts Maritime Academy Oceanography course, Spring 2017.
- Teaching Assistant for MIT *The History of Earth's Climate*, Spring 2017. Overall TA Rating: 7.0/7.0 [Evaluations]. Lead instructor: David McGee.
- Teaching Assistant for MIT *Climate Science*, Fall 2016. Overall TA Rating: 6.9/7.0 [Evaluations]. Lead instructors: Kerry Emanuel & Edward Boyle.
- Teaching Assistant for MIT Sedimentology in the Field: Precambrian Environments, Spring 2016. Overall TA Rating: 6.7/7.0 [Evaluations]. Lead instructor: Kristin Bergmann.
- Teaching Assistant for University of Arizona Summer Field Geology Camp, Summer 2015, half term (2.5 weeks). Lead instructor: Jay Quade.
- Teaching Assistant for Princeton Earth's Environments and Ancient Civilizations, Fall 2012. Lead instructors: Adam Maloof & Frederik Simons.

# LEADERSHIP

- Co-founder of Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders in Geosciences. 2021.
- Panelist for AGU's Cultivating Leadership for Change and Justice in the Geosciences: "Progress and lessons learned after one year of anti-racism efforts in the geosciences." May 2021.
- Panelist for "Sitting Down with Uncomfortable Things in the Caltech Archives," part of the institute-wide *Critical Intersections: Conversations on History, Race, and Science* seminar series organized by the Division of Humanities and Social Sciences. October 2020. [LA Times]
- Panelist for session on *Diversity and Inclusion in the Quaternary Sciences*, American Quaternary Association (AmQua) 50th anniversary meeting. June 2020.
- AmQua Ad-hoc Diversity Committee, member. 2020.
- MIT EAPS Resource for Easing Friction and Stress (EAPS REFS), 2017–2019. Serving as a trained graduate student mediator to provide low barrier, confidential peer-to-peer coaching, listening, de-escalation, informal mentoring and mediation for the department.
- Creator and facilitator of a 1.5-hour interactive workshop on Growing Healthy Labs: Effective Leadership of Research Groups.
- MIT Women in Course 12 (WiXII), Vice President (Fall 2016) & Board Member (2016–2017).
- Princeton Undergraduate Geosciences Society, Co-founder and President, 2011–2013.

#### SERVICE

- AGU Diversity and Inclusion Advisory Committee, 2022–present.
- Panelist for Earth Science Women's Network Careers Outside Academia, November 2021.
- Invited facilitator for workshop on remote mentoring of summer undergraduate researchers, hosted by Society for Women in Marine Science, June 2020.
- Community Partner for Princeton Pace Center for Civic Engagement's RISE (Recognizing Inequalities and Standing for Equality) Initiative. 2020.
- Legal Observer, National Lawyers Guild, Los Angeles chapter. 2020.
- Panelist for *Professional and Graduate School Panel Discussion*, hosted by MIT Office of Undergraduate Advising and Academic Programming and Office of Graduate Education. April 2018.
- Science Planning Meeting, NSF Continental Scientific Drilling Coordination Office. Nov 2016.

#### PEER REVIEW

• Reviewer for *Nature Geoscience*, National Science Foundation, *Geobiology*, *Journal of Quaternary Science*, National Geographic Society, American Chemical Society. 2017–present.

# Public Engagement

- Active Twitter for science communication (@earth2christine), 3,000+ followers. 2012-present.
- Speaker for Exploring By The Seat of Your Pants, video broadcast into classrooms. April 2019.
- Speaker for CafeSci Boston at the Boston Public Library, "Decoding the Climate from Ancient Lakes and Caves," hosted by NOVA and WGBH Educational Foundation. March 2019.
- "Resident Geologist" of HBO's Westworld (TV series) on Reddit, author of a post explaining the tufa towers of the Trona Pinnacles in Searles Valley, a major filming site for the series. 13k views. Picked up by Harper's Bazaar and YouTube channel Alt Shift X.
- Letters to a Pre-Scientist, Pen Pal. 2016–2018.
- Created a science booth on how geologists reconstruct past rainfall patterns, presenting at MIT Museum Girls Day (March 2018), MIT Environmental Solutions Initiative Earth Day Celebration (April 2018), Cambridge Science Festival (2016, 2017, 2018), MIT Open House (2017), and the annual John H. Carlson Lecture at the New England Aquarium (2015, 2016).
- 8th grade Earth science class from Dana Hall School, final field trip assistant. May 2017.
- Northeast Regional Middle School Science Bowl Competition, Moderator. February 2017.
- Science Club for Girls, K-1st After School Program, Mentor Scientist (5 hrs/wk). Fall 2016.
- National Geographic Young Explorers Workshop, Washington D.C., USA. June 2016.
- Project Scientist, STEM Superstar for Charlotte, North Carolina. June 2016.
- Princeton Community House After School Academy, tutor and mentor, 2009–2011.
- Science blog about experience as a geologic field assistant in South Australia. Summer 2010.

# FIELD WORK & OTHER FIELD EXPERIENCE

- 2020 Death Valley & Searles Lake, CA (PI for 2 weeks): Tufas and paleoshorelines
- 2018 Searles Lake, CA (PI for 4.5 weeks): Tufas and paleoshorelines of Searles Valley
- 2017 Searles Lake, CA (10 days): Continental drilling of lake sediments from Searles Lake bed
- 2016 Altiplano and Atacama, Chile (PI for 4 weeks): Central Andes paleolake levels
- 2016 Van Horn, Texas (9 days, teaching assistant): Precambrian sedimentology
- 2015 Lake Junín (Chinchaycocha), Peru (one month): ICDP drilling of lake sediments
- 2015 Western U.S., University of Arizona Summer Field School (2.5 weeks, student TA)
- 2015 Altiplano and Atacama, Chile (PI for 5 weeks): Central Andes paleolake levels
- 2014 Utah, Nevada (2 weeks, field assistant): Lake Bonneville lake and cave carbonates
- 2014 Utah, New Mexico (9 days, class assistant): 3D drone mapping of ancient landscapes
- 2012 Utah, Idaho, and Nevada (PI for 9 weeks): Lake Bonneville shoreline features
- 2012 Cyprus (10 days, class TA): Geophysical survey of Polis Chrysochous archeology site
- 2011 South Australia (8 weeks, field assistant): Ediacaran carbonates, Shuram anomaly

### OTHER SKILLS

Proficient: MATLAB, LaTeX, ArcGIS, Adobe Illustrator and Photoshop Intermediate: Git, Python, C++, C, Java, HTML

Tier 3 Conflict Management Training (40 hours), Conflict Management@MIT, Spring 2017.